Guide to the International Monitor Institute. Middle East videotapes, 1991-2008 RL.00606
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Middle East videotapes, circa 1991-2008, 80 boxes
  - Kurdish Tape #2, PAL VHS [TRT:2:00:00] (Box 349: 2 copies; Box 413: 1 original) (Box 349 and 413, Video-cassette ME094)
    Original Credits: LR #4-Quality varying to not so good at times on part A, no sound except music on part A. Part B good quality.
    One original tape divided into two betas and two working copies.
    Tape A(00:58:00): Shots of mass graves, people digging up bones, with people surrounding sites, some shots dated 1991 Nov. 7, shots of fields strewn with bones outside unidentified towns, or graveyards? Shots of people marching carrying signs that say Halabja and demonstrating interspersed with shots back to people digging bones out of the ground, demonstrators come to spot where the graves are being dug up. Shots of UN officers at scene taking photographs. Later shots dated 1991 Aug. 11, very short interviews with people, clothes being dug up from graves surrounded by mourners, some very brief shots dated 1991 Nov. 11, but of very poor quality, including perspective shots of the surrounding area showing ruins of a fort. End of tape has a funeral procession.
    Tape B (01:02:00): Shots of injured Kurds describing what happened and how they incurred their injuries, includes young girls and boys as well as adults and old women, they are asked their names and where they are from and what happened to them, shows dated of 1991 Sep. 16, many of the people on the video seemed to be effected by chemical weapons by the nature of their wounds, disfigured arms, hands, and legs, and they discuss chemical weapons attacks and their experiences, a lot of the injuries seem to be of land mine attacks.
  - Baghdad Television Summary: BAG 99-338 - FBIS Tape [1999 Dec. 14], NTSC VHS [TRT:1:00:00] (Box 349: 1 copy; Box 413: 1 original) (Box 349 and 413, Video-cassette ME095)
    Producer: Baghdad Television
    Original Credits: From World News Connection
    Saddam Husayn awarded Revolutionary Command Council [RCC] and Ba'th party members medals of valor. (Video clip of Saddam, in a civilian attire, entering a hall; Saddam, RCC members, and Ba'th party members standing listening to head of presidential office Ahmad Khudayyir reading presidential decrees awarding them medals of valor; Saddam Husayn decorating officials with medals of valor; Saddam sitting, addressing the officials and congratulating them on the blessed month of Ramadan and on their medals. He then began to speak about historical background of the meaning of medals. Izzat Ibrahim then congratulates the president on the blessed month of Ramadan, praises his leadership, and pledges to continue march under his leadership. Vice President Taha Yasin Ramadan then congratulates the president, praises his great leadership, and pledges to continue march under his leadership. Badr-al-Din Muddaththir, member of the Iraqi Ba'th party's national command in Sudan, congratulates the president on the blessed month of Ramadan, reviews the Arab situation and praises Saddam's leadership. Saddam then comments briefly on what other officials said and says that Iraq is an example to the arab nation and its struggle. He says that although the Iraqi people are besieged, they confront the aggressors.
  - Kurdish Tape #3 (Kirkuk, Suleimaniya, Refugees, BBC Newsnight Investigation against Chemical Weapons), PAL VHS [TRT:2:18:00] (Box 349: 2 copies; Box 413: 1 original) (Box 349 and 413, Video-cassette ME096)
    Original Credits: Tape A: LR #5. Tape B: LR #3
    Tape A (01:33:00): Tape Labeled Kirkuk 1991 Mar. and Suleimaniya 1991 Apr. 28:
    First part dated on tape 1991 Mar. 21, taped from a car, showing the outskirts of Kirkuk municipality in days just after Gulf War, shows people defacing pictures of Saddam Hussein as well as already defaced pictures, also shows destruction wrecked cars, etc. Shows security offices with Kurdish soldiers outside, includes footage of some destroyed buildings and tanks, includes shots of the area outside Kirkuk, includes shots of Kurdish soldiers, cheering Kurds, brief interviews with Kurds discussing situation and collaborators(?), interviews in English translated about experiences in prison camp, discussing situation after revolution release of prisoners, includes shots of children with guns made out of metal, also includes scenes of children injured in hospitals, victims of Iraqi chemical and phosphorus chemical attacks, and interviews with their parents explaining what happened to them in Kurdish translated into English, interviews with doctors about emergency supplies, etc. for Suleimaniya, shots of people digging up grounds of security offices looking for bodies, places where women have been raped, evidence proving rapes of women, shots of Masoud Barzani (?), meeting with various fighters, peshmerga, shots of refugees on the roads of Kurdistan.
    Tape B (01:17:00): Continues from original tape labeled Kirkuk/Suleimaniya. Showing refugees by the road walking in mud, women and children, children carrying guns, people camping besides the road, shots of the burial of a baby and shots of another dead baby, Kurds supplicating for help from United Nations, other shots of extreme squalid conditions experienced in refugee camps.
    Middle East Watch / Newsnight Broadcast from 1993 June 22, BBC News program on Saddam's vendetta against the Kurds, the Anfal, and evidence of attempt to annihilate the Kurds, shots of the Arbil Municipal cemetery and it's use as a dumping ground by Iraqi security forces, and exhumations by Kurds after Iraqi troops left to identify missing loved ones, including young 13 year old boy identified, story of ethnic hatred, comparison of destruction of Kurds in Anfal to the Holocaust, destruction of villages, with a picture of Ali Hassan Al Majid and evidence, attempt to get eyewitness account of destruction of chemical attack on Goptapa, eyewitness by headman of village, shots of aftermath of another attack dated 1988 May 16, recording of a meeting by Ali Hassan al-Majid advocating using chemical weapons against their own people, Khorah Two fort, holding center for prisoners destroyed by Iraqi's as they left, stories of two survivors of firing squads, Hama Ali, taken to Topzawa site of burials near Kirkuk, where the women and children were taken away then the men put into hole and killed, another man's story of being driven into the desert to be shot and buried with bulldozers, shots of women holding pictures of lost family men, evidence of a new more recent massacre, scenes of torture chambers, situation on border of security zone lack of ability to defend their land, powerless against Iraqi army, sort of premonition to situation in 1996 when Saddam retook Kirkuk, lack of allied response to protect Kurds on the ground, eyewitness accounts of killing of civilians by Kurdish children, shots of recent terrorist attacks carried out by Kurdish agents of Saddam, 35 separate incidents, economic relation with Baghdad.
    Newsline (English Show) with Ed Bradley reporter, Clive Snow, forensic anthropologist investigating mass graves, corroborating story of mass murders by Saddam Hussein, Andrew Whitley, Director of Human Rights Watch, investigates Saddam's problem with the Kurds, Jamal Amin tells story of imprisonment by secret police, destruction of Kurdish villages taped by Iraqi security, story of Taymour, shots of chemical attacks on Kurdish villages.
  - Kurdish Tape #4-British News Clips on Situation of Kurdish Refugees, PAL VHS [TRT:2:43:35] (Box 349: 2 copies; Box 413: 1 original) (Box 349 and 413, Video-cassette ME097)
    Original Credits: INDICT Tape #10
    News Clips circa 1991 Apr. on two Betas and two working copies.
    British news clips over several days on the creation of safe havens for the Kurds and the situation of the Kurds fleeing the troops of Saddam Hussein after the Kurdish uprising after the Gulf War.
    Tape A:
    1-(00:00:00) Iraqi incursion in Iran to chase Kurdish Refugees with some footage of food drops, John Scofield, World News Desk, 1,000 refugees / day dying, loadmaster Kevin Boone, US Army, with Ann Clwyd, Labour Foreign Affairs Spokeswoman, David Nabarro, Ch. Advisor, Overseas Dev. Administration, on situation of Kurdish refugees.
    2-(00:05:08) Discussion in English Parliament of seeking to overthrow Saddam Hussein from power, why wasn't overthrown out, and helping the Kurdish refugees, Douglas Hurd, MP Robert Hughes, Lab. Overseas Development, Ann Clwyd.
    3-(00:10:31) Discussion of failure of governments to help Kurds and Shiis in Iraq in the House of Lords, Lord Cledwyn of Penrhos, Leader of Labour Peers, calls it genocide, Lord Caithness, Foreign Office Minister, the use of troops to protect Kurds, Lord Bonham-Carter, Liberal Democrat.
    4-(00:14:02) Kurdish refugees inside Sar Dasht, Iran, shots of sick and injured children, Kurdish refugee camps.
    5-(00:14:44) Dying of Kurdish refugees along the Kurdish border, criticism of Bush administration, Bush spokesman.
    6-(00:15:25) Peshmerga guerrillas, Andrew Simmons, ITN reporter, could have done more with support, footage on situation of demobilized guerilla fighters and their families.
    7-(00:17:18) Situation of UN aid, and situation of Kurdish refugees in Sar Dasht, Iran, footage of refugees, living conditions, hospitals and shots of sick children, phosphorus burns, Ghassem Resh crossing points between Iran and Iraq, Clarence Mitchell, BBC News reporter, and David Wyatt, British Red Cross on underestimation of Kurdish post-war refugee crisis, the scale of crisis, criticism of governments for allowing situation to exist in the first place.
    8-(00:25:33) Neil Kinnock MP, Leader of Labour Opposition, Saddam has a case to answer for the subject of genocide, bringing Saddam to trial.
    9-(00:26:07) ITN, Turkish border situation, Glen Oglaza, reporter on Turkish border, distribution of aid to refugees, shots of situation, separation by Saddam of men from their families, reports of atrocities.
    10-(00:27:28) Reports of sending troops into Iraq to help distribute aid, for humanitarian assistance, call for action to help Kurds, Gavin Esler, criticism of Bush administration, Bob Hall, Pentagon spokesman.
    11-(00:29:37) Report on missions, Jeremy Bowen, footage of transport of aid, Turkish firing into the air to drive back refugees, Turkey-Iraq border, situation on Iran border.
    12-(00:33:15) SIX News, situation on Turkish border camp at Silopi. Michael Macmillan,SE Turkey, search for asylum, refugees don't want to go back.
    13-(00:35:10) Safe havens for the Kurds, John Major seeking legal advice on genocide terms of Saddam Hussein, Turkish criticism by Vildirim Akbulut, Turkish Prime Minister, of foreign aid to the Kurds in Turkey.
    14-(00:36:50) Saadoun Hammadi, Prime Minister Iraq, talking about elections in Iraq, John Simpson in Iraq, under Iraqi government restrictions, shots of Saddam Hussein, Saddam staying in power depends on Iraqi people, new constitution, president will be elected.
    15-(00:40:13) Channel Four News, aid to the Kurdish refugees, deciding to send British troops and level of British aid, twice as many refugees in Iran, but much less aid than going to Turkish border, shots of long line going to border and walking across mountain passes, Shiite refugees into Iran, German aid, reports of atrocities for those who tried to return, David Jones, Oxfam on the need for protection of aid agencies by troops, UN sponsored aid workers plan, Eric Suy, UN envoy to Iraq, discussing UN presence in north and south, Yildirim Akbulut, Ann Perkins political correspondent, on creating safe havens.
    16- (00:49:53) Corporal Kevin High, Royal Air Force, role of rescuers, having to leave people behind.
    17-(00:50:20) Risk of vetos of safe havens, Turkish policy, footage of Miss Sadaka Odaku, lack of money on the part of UN, movement of Kurdish refugees off mountains to Silopi.
    18-(00:51:51) The distribution of aid on the part of American troops, Michael Brunson, reporter, British use of troops on safe havens.
    19-(00:54:50) Bringing charges against Saddam for war crimes, by request from Council of Ministers, Ken Rees on Saddam Hussein, and trial in abstention mocked by Saddam, list of war crimes against Geneva convention include torture of Kuwaits resistance, use of hostages as human shields, tried by special tribunal or by Kuwait, Evelyn Le Chene, war crimes expert.
    20-(00:57:58) Saddam's attack on returning Kurdish refugees, freshly dug graves cover the mountain side, situation of old people, Tent city in Silopi, Geoffrey Archer, Nick Bouian, Royal Air Force plan to help refugees.
    21-(01:02:43) Reporters, John Major on terms of safe havens, proposals to get Kurds down off the mountains and into safe havens, length of British involvement, criticism of too little too late.
    22-(01:06:58) Bush speech announces relief aids, no military intervention into Iraq's internal affairs, safe haven reports, and humanitarian, Gavin Esler. No apology for asking Iraqi people to rebel, John Harrison, reporter on safe havens, Fergus Walsh, reports on aid to Kurds, military relief camps, to encourage Kurds to come down from mountains, Hoshyar Zebari, Kurdistan Front, Prof Adam Roberts, Balliol College, Oxford, commenting on situation, footage of scenes in refugee camps, request by Iraq to sell oil to buy food.
    23-(01:15:20) Refugees on the Iranian border, footage of camps on Iranian border, Piranshah, Iranian border town, witness statements by refugees of misery experienced, shots of crossing points between Iran and Iraq, Clarence Mitchell, BBC News.
    24-(01:20:00) John Major on returning Kurds, Menzies Campbell MP, Liberal Democrat spokesman, George Robertson MP, Labour Foreign Affairs spokesman.
    25-(01:22:08) Bush relenting to pressure, if Saddam was to step down could find asylum in another country, critics of Bush, Bill Neeley, ITN reporter, reaction of Kurdish refugees reported by Glen Oglaza from Turkey, biggest relief effort of all times, Muntaez Mufti, Kurdish Human Rights Organization, commenting on what the Kurds want, questioning the length of the effort, Desmond Harney, Middle East Expert, commenting on length, Ann Clwyd reporting on offer by Saddam for Kurdish autonomy to Jalal Talabani.
    Tape B:
    1-(01:32:50) Continuation of last with Gerald Kaufman MP, shadow foreign secretary on statement of Saddam giving autonomy to Kurds and the plan to use British soldiers in mercy missions to protect Kurdish refugees.
    2-(01:35:20) Michael Brunson, political editor, on humanitarian mission and it's politics, UN backed operation.
    3-(01:37:30) The relief operation and Baghdad's opposition, John Major interview, Bush announcement, Hoshyar Zebari, Kurdistan Front, shots of situation in Kurdistan, David Shukman, correspondent, shots of the relief organization, condemnation of Iraq, footage of Kurds in mountains, Aga Khan as rep of UN to get aid to Kurds, French president Mitterand and French plan, Bernard Kouchner, Aid minister, Peres de Cuellar on plan, Piranshah on Iranian border.
    4-(01:48:20) Peter Gould reporting on Lynda Chalker MP, Overseas Development Minister facing committee in English Parliament on refugees and the British plan to help them.
    5-(01:49:30) Conditions in the mountains being crossed by the Kurds (repeated report), condemnation by Iraq of plan, effecting plan by UN to bring aid to Iraqi people, agreement cancelled by Iraqis at last moment, growing sense of desperation.
    6-(01:52:18) Channel Four News report on American troops being sent, long term consequences of sending in the troops to Iraq.
    7-(01:53:25) Abdul Amir al-Anbari, Iraqi ambassador to UN opposing the sending of troops to Iraq, Foreign Secretary Douglas Hurd on temporary nature of camps, Gerald Kaufman MP statement, the details of the plan, Douglass Hogg MP, Pete Williams US Defense Dept spokesman, on details of American plan, John Kerry US Senator on involvement, question of motivation on part of Bush, Peter Galbraith, Senate Foreign Relations Committee on immorality of Bush and the details of the plan.
    8-(02:01:17) Richard Armitage, US State Dept discussing American involvement and defending American policy, comparison to Palestinian situation, no to Vietnam analogy.
    9-(02:04:41) Channel Four News, The Problems ahead with the humanitarian effort, footage of Kurdish refugees in Turkey, Nadhim Zahawi, Kurdish exile discussing ground forces, Lynda Chalker MP on priorities.
    10-(02:07:05) Humanitarian camps, the numbers, near Zakho and Dahuk, health situation among Kurds, footage of Kurds in mountains.
    11-(02:11:00) Richard Armitage and American policy change towards the Kurds, Peter Galbraith.
    12-(02:12:40) Skepticism towards Iraq and Saddam, Peter Gowring reporter, Rosalyn Higgins, Prof of International Law, LSE, comparisons to Palestinian camps.
    13-(02:14:10) Can the camps help, effect on Iran of having US troops help them, most of refugees in Iran, details of the operation along the Turkish border, the pressure on Iran of the refugees coping on it's own without western aid, Lynda Chalker MP on situation in Iran, resolution 688 about the Kurds.
    14-(02:21:04) John Major on project in Iraq, call for help with southern Iraqi refugees, Siyamand Banna, Kurdish Democratic Front.
    15-(02:22:35) Safe havens, Jonathan Charles reporter, James Baker what the allies can achieve, meeting of ministers.
    16-(02:24:50) Ann Clwyd in Parliament on the situation, reply by Douglas Hurd, Peter Shore, Foreign Affairs Committee of Britain questioning Lynda Chalker, on efforts for aid to Kurds, Jim Lester, Dennis Canavan, Ivan Lawrence on limited role of troops protection of Kurdish troops and right to intervene in Iraq, Dick Cheney, Tariq Aziz saying that they don't have right to intervene, Iraq signing aid agreement with UN, disagreement, footage of Kurds, Geoffrey Archer.
    17-(02:36:51) Which British troops will join the humanitarian effort, suitable sites for refugee camps, David Shukman reporter on the delivering of food, footage of stampedes.
    18-(02:36:26) Situation in Iran helping the refugees, Charles Wheeler from Piranshah, miserable shelters of plastic, choice between buying shelter or food, closing of Iranian border by Iranian, difference of altitude, footage of miserable conditions of refugees in rain.
    19-(02:41:20) Sick refugees, suffering of children in Cokurca camp, reuniting of a woman with her family, providing for help within Iraq.
  - Kurdish Tape #5-Two Dispatches Documentaries and British News Clips, PAL VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 349: 2 copies; Box 412: 1 original) (Box 349 and 412, Video-cassette ME098)
    Original Credits: Christmas in Kurdistan. Associate Producer: Chris Ledger. Producer: Chris Oxley. Director: Michael Sposito (Canadian Reporter)
    Tape A: Dispatches Documentary 1: Christmas In Kurdistan
    Situation in Kurdistan near Iraqi-Iranian border after the Gulf War, Winter of 1991, safe havens don't seem to be working, uneasy truce between the Kurds and regime of Saddam Hussein, squeezing the Kurds at checkpoints taking gas and food. Documentary to see the effect of the safe havens for the Kurds, and the failure of the safe havens to protect the Kurds, documenting miserable conditions in the refugee camps, interviews with Kurdish villagers wanting Saddam out, Medecins Sans Frontiers discussing hopeless medical situation, hostility of Turks and situation with relief agencies, footage of uprising battles in Kirkuk, defacing images of Saddam, two million refugees after Saddam retook Kirkuk and oil cities, John Major's proposal of safe havens and return of Kurds to homes. Shows how fighting hadn't stopped after creation of safe havens, interview with Jalal Talabani, Leader of Patriotic Union of Kurdistan. Interview with Jim Reynolds, UN High Commission for Refugees on the situation of the Kurdish refugees in the camps. Saddam cut off the gas from the Kurds hoping for infighting, no milk, food as well, cut all supplies. Footage of demonstrations in Suleymaniya to protect refugees and to help Kurdish people. Interview with Michael Stopford, Chief Officer, UN Gulf Aid, plan to help refugees on the ground now, Ann Clwyd, Shadow Minister, Overseas Aid, flouting of UN resolution to help Kurds, Douglas Hogg, Minister of State, Foreign Affairs, defending British government policy.
    (00:40:37) Tape A: Dispatches Documentary 2: The Audit of War
    What were the true costs of the Gulf War one year later and the responsibility and morality of the Americans. Billions of pounds moved from third world to the first world. Starts with a one-sided celebration of US power, the Gulf War cost $70 billion yet US and Britain spent very little because they were reimbursed. Interviews with Gordon Adams, Defence Budget Analyst, argues that US might have made a profit, war from the Western side a clean war, a bloodless victory, George Joffe, Economist Intelligence Unit, yet inside Iraq the losses were horrendous, possibly 200,000 civilian deaths in one month, Dr. Paul Rogers, Bradford University, did Iraq deserve what their rulers were doing? Untreated sewage flowing into streets and rivers. Jean Dreze, author of "Hunger and Poverty in Iraq", the grave mortality rate among children, the deaths in the abortive rebellions after the war encouraged by Bush, Humphrey Harrison, Analyst, Middle East Affairs, effect on Arab opinions, US Army Showcase Jamboree in Washington, enthusiastic selling of arms, arms salesman victory in the war, Admiral Gene Le Roque, Center for Defence Information, up to 1990 sales to third world dropped after they jumped, Saudis to build up armed forces, a new armed race not good for New World Order of Middle East Peace, Congressman Lee Hamilton, importance of peace. Situation in Yemen during the war, expulsion of Yemenis from Arab countries for voting against the war, virtually unreported in press, Dr. Hassan Makki, Deputy Prime Minister, Yemen, Dr. Abdul Aziz, Editor, Yemen Times, stop of aid to Yemen, causing breakdown in services. Stuart McNab, UNICEF, and Badar al-Humadi, Kuwaiti Development Fund, Who benefited from the war, companies to help clean up the vandalism of the war, British businessmen, Hermann Simon, Man. Kuwait International Hotel, David Gund, Ed. Gulf Reconstruction Report, Geoff Chandler, Graffitti Clean, John Royall, ICMX, Bill Richardson, Babcock Construction The Environmental catastrophe to stifle discussion of the disaster by the American and Kuwaiti government on long term health, Paul Horsman, Greenpeace, Dr. Fatima Abdali, Kuwaiti Research Scientist, Humphrey Harrison, Oil analyst, the future controlling the oil, and the future of oil prices and the effect on economies of third world companies again not reported or discussed in Western press, battle between Kuwait and Saudi between oil prices, and potential glut, consequences on the Middle East of lowering oil prices. Peter Odell, International Oil Consultant, Keeping the Peace, the New World Order based on confrontation rather than negotiation and effects on ordinary people of the Middle East, massive force, desire for Israeli-Palestinian peace, lack of democracy in Gulf, Saddam still in power.
    Senator Joseph Lieberman, war worth it; Senator Lee Hamilton, war not worth it.
    Tape B: (01:01:00) Various British Television news clips.
  - Amnesty International: Kuwait Electronic News Release (ENR), NTSC VHS [TRT:0:14:00] (Box 353, Video-cassette ME099)